<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached November 5, 1678, at St. Margarets Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons by John Tillotson ...</title>
            <author>Tillotson, John, 1630-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217946</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13153474</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13153474</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62594)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 752:24, 2046:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached November 5, 1678, at St. Margarets Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons by John Tillotson ...</title>
                  <author>Tillotson, John, 1630-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for Brabazon Aylmer ..., and W. Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Item at 752:24 is identified as T1230; item at 2046:15 is identified as T1229A. Items otherwise identical.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke IX, 55-56 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98129:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98129:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED <hi>November</hi> 5. 1678. AT <hi>St.</hi> MARGARETS <hi>Westminſter,</hi> Before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS.</p>
            <p>By JOHN TILLOTSON, D. D. Dean of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer,</hi> at the three Pigeons over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> And <hi>William Rogers,</hi> at the Maiden-head over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:98129:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98129:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the Honourable Houſe of Commons, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 5. 1678.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LUKE 9.55, 56.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But he turned, and rebuked them, and ſaid, Ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of; For the Son of Man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong many other Things, which may juſtly recommend the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of mankind, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick goodneſs of it is moſt apt to make impreſſion upon the Minds of ſerious and conſiderate men. The Miracles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98129:3"/>of it are the great external evidence and confirmation of its truth and Divinity; but the morality of its Doctrines and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, ſo agreeable to the beſt Reaſon, and wiſeſt apprehenſions of mankind, ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably fitted for the perfecting of our natures, and the ſweetning of the ſpirits and tempers of men, ſo friendly to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Society, and every way ſo well calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated for the peace and order of the World. Theſe are the things which our Religion glories in as her crown and excellency. <hi>Miracles</hi> are apt to awaken and aſtoniſh, and by a ſenſible and over-powering evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to bear down the prejudices of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity; but there are ſecret charms in <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> which take faſt hold of the hearts of men and do inſenſibly, but effectually, command our love and eſteem.</p>
            <p>And ſurely nothing can be more proper to the occaſion of this Day, than a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon this Argument; which ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly tends to correct that unchriſtian ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and miſtaken zeal, which hath been the cauſe of all our troubles and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98129:3"/>and had ſo powerful an influence upon that horrid Tragedy, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, now near upon fourſcore years ago, to have been acted as upon this Day.</p>
            <p>And that we may the better underſtand the reaſon of our Saviour's reproof here in the Text, it will be requiſite to conſider the occaſion of this hot and furious zeal, which appeared in ſome of his Diſciples. And that was this, Our Saviour was going from <hi>Galilee</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and being to paſs through a Village of <hi>Samaria,</hi> he ſent meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers before him, to prepare entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for him; but the People of that Place would not receive him, becauſe he was going to <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> The reaſon whereof was, the <hi>difference of Religion,</hi> which then was between the <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Samaritans.</hi> Of which I ſhall give you this brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Samaritans</hi> were originally that Colony of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> which we find in the Book of <hi>Kings,</hi> was, upon the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the Ten Tribes, planted in <hi>Samaria</hi> by <hi>Salmanaſſar.</hi> They were Heathens, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98129:4"/>worſhipped their own Idols, till they were ſo infeſted with Lions, that for the redreſs of this miſchief they deſired to be inſtructed in the worſhip of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> hoping by this means to appeaſe the anger of the God of the Country; and then they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> together with their own Idols; for ſo it is ſaid in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Kings,</hi> That <hi>they feared the Lord, and ſerved their own Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> were returned from the Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was rebuilt, all the <hi>Jews</hi> were obliged by a ſolemn Covenant to put away their <hi>Heathen</hi> Wives. It happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Prieſt, had married the Daughter of <hi>Sanballat</hi> the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan;</hi> and being unwilling to put away his Wife, <hi>Sanballat</hi> excited the <hi>Samaritans</hi> to build a Temple upon Mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> near the City of <hi>Samaria,</hi> in oppoſition to the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and made <hi>Manaſſes;</hi> his Son in Law; Prieſt there.</p>
            <p>Upon the building of this new Temple, there aroſe a great feud between the <hi>Jews</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98129:4"/>and <hi>Samaritans,</hi> which in proceſs of time grew to ſo violent a hatred, that they would not ſo much as ſhew common civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to one another. And this was the reaſon why the <hi>Samaritans</hi> would not receive our Saviour in his journey, becauſe they perceived he was going to worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this uncivil uſage of our Saviour, <hi>two</hi> of his Diſciples, <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> preſently take fire, and out of a well-meaning zeal for the honour of their Maſter, and of the true God, and of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the true place of his worſhip, they are immediatly for diſpatching out of the way theſe Enemies of God, and Chriſt, and the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, theſe <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> for ſo they called one another: And to this end they deſire our Saviour to give them power to <hi>call for fire from Heaven to conſume them,</hi> as <hi>Elias</hi> had done in a like caſe, and that too not far from <hi>Samaria;</hi> and it is not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that their being ſo near the place where <hi>Elias</hi> had done the like before, might prompt them to this requeſt.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98129:5"/>
            <p>Our Saviour ſeeing them in this heat notwithſtanding all the reaſons they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for their paſſion, and for all they ſheltered themſelves under the great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Elias,</hi> doth very calmly, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverely reprove this temper of theirs, <hi>You know not what manner of Spirit ye are of; for the Son of Man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grotius</hi> obſerves, that theſe two excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sentences are left out in a <hi>Manuſcript</hi> that is in <hi>England.</hi> I cannot tell what <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript</hi> he refers to, but if it were a Copy written out in the height of Popery, no wonder if ſome zealous Tranſcriber of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at this paſſage, ſtruck it out of the Goſpel, being confident our Saviour would not ſay any thing, that was ſo directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the current Doctrine and practice of thoſe times. But thanks be to God, this admirable <hi>Saying</hi> is ſtill preſerv'd, and can never be made uſe of upon a fitter oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of: That is,</hi> Ye own your ſelves to be my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98129:5"/>Diſciples, but do you conſider what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit now acts and governs you? Not <hi>that</hi> ſurely which my Doctrine deſigns to mould and faſhion you into, which is not a furious and perſecuting and deſtructive ſpirit, but mild and gentle and ſaving; tender of the lives and intereſts of men, even of thoſe who are our greateſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: You ought to conſider, That you are not now under the rough and ſowr Diſpenſation of the Law, but the calm and peaceable Inſtitution of the Goſpel; to which the Spirit of <hi>Elias,</hi> though he was a very good man in his time, would be altogether unſuitable. God permitted it then, under that imperfect way of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but now under the Goſpel it would be intolerable: For that deſigns univerſal love, and peace, and good-will; and now no difference of Religion, no pretence of zeal for God and Chriſt can warrant and juſtifie this paſſionate and fierce, this vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictive and exterminating ſpirit:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Son of Man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> He ſays in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98129:6"/>elſe-where, that he <hi>was not come to ſend Peace, but a Sword;</hi> which we are not to underſtand of the natural tendency of his Religion, but of the accidental event and effect of it, through the malice and perverſneſs of Men: But here he ſpeaks of the proper intention and deſign of his coming; <hi>He</hi> came not to kill and deſtroy, but <hi>for the healing of the Nations;</hi> for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and redemption of Mankind, not only <hi>from the wrath to come,</hi> but from a great part of the evils and miſeries of this life: <hi>He</hi> came to diſcountenance all fierceneſs and rage and cruelty in men, one towards another; to reſtrain and ſubdue that furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and unpeaceable Spirit, which is ſo troubleſome to the world, and the cauſe of ſo many miſchiefs and diſorders in it: And to introduce a Religion which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults not only the eternal Salvation of mens ſouls, but their temporal peace and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, their comfort and happineſs in this world.</p>
            <p>The <hi>words</hi> thus explain'd contain this <hi>Obſervation, That a revengeful and cruel and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98129:6"/>deſtructive Spirit, is directly contrary to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and temper of the Goſpel, and not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed upon any pretence of zeal for God and Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this Argument, I ſhall confine my Diſcourſe to theſe <hi>Three</hi> heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To ſhew the oppoſition of this ſpirit to the true Spirit and deſign of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The unjuſtifiableneſs of it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any pretence of zeal for God and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To apply this Diſcourſe to the occaſion of this Day.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall ſhew <hi>the oppoſition of this ſpirit to the true Spirit and deſign of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion:</hi> That it is directly oppoſite to the main and fundamental <hi>Precepts</hi> of the Goſpel; and to the great <hi>Paterns</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of our Religion, our bleſſed <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> and the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This ſpirit which our Saviour here reproves in his Diſciples, is directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the main and fundamental <hi>Precepts</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98129:7"/>of the Goſpel; which command us to <hi>love one another,</hi> and <hi>to love all men,</hi> even our very <hi>enemies;</hi> and are ſo far from permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us to perſecute thoſe who hate us, that they forbid us to hate thoſe who perſecute us: They require us, to be <hi>merciful, as our Father which is in Heaven is merciful;</hi> to be <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>tender-hearted, forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrel againſt any, even as God for Chriſt's ſake hath forgiven us:</hi> And <hi>to put on, as the elect of God, bowels of mercy, meekneſs and long-ſuffering,</hi> and to <hi>follow peace with all men,</hi> and to <hi>ſhew all meekneſs to all men:</hi> And particularly the Paſtors and Governors of the Church are eſpecially charged to be of this temper: <hi>The ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle unto all men; apt to teach, in meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if peradventure God will give them repentance to the acknowledgment of the truth.</hi> To all which <hi>Precepts,</hi> and many more that I might reckon up, nothing can be more plainly oppoſite, than inhumane Cruelties and Perſections, treacherous Conſpiracies.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98129:7"/>and bloody Maſſacres, a barbarous Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and a <hi>holy League</hi> to extirpate all that differ from us. And in ſtead of <hi>inſtructing in meekneſs thoſe that oppoſe themſelves,</hi> to convert men with fire and faggot, and to teach them, as <hi>Gideon</hi> did the <hi>men of Succoth, with briars and thorns;</hi> and inſtead of waiting for their repentance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and endeavouring to recover them out of the ſnare of the Devil, to put them quick into his hands, and to diſpatch them to hell as faſt as is poſſible. If the precepts of Chriſtianity can be contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, ſurely it cannot be done more groſly and palpably than by ſuch practiſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Spirit is likewiſe directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the great <hi>paterns</hi> and examples of our Religion, our <hi>bleſſed Saviour,</hi> and the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians.</hi> It was propheſied of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> that he ſhould be <hi>the Prince of peace;</hi> and ſhould make it one of his great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes upon earth, to make peace in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth; to reconcile men to God, and to one another; to take up all thoſe feuds, and to extinguiſh all thoſe animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities that were in the world; to bring to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98129:8"/>agreement and a peaceable demeanour one towards another thoſe that were moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in their tempers and intereſts, to <hi>make the lamb and the wolf lie down together, that there might be no more deſtroying nor devouring in all God's holy mountain; that is,</hi> that <hi>that</hi> cruel and deſtructive ſpirit which prevailed before in the world, ſhould then be baniſhed out of all Chriſtian ſocieties.</p>
            <p>And in conformity to theſe predictions, when our Saviour was born into the world, the Angels ſang that heavenly <hi>Anthem, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God in the higheſt, peace on earth, and good will among men.</hi> And when he appeared in the world, his whole life and carriage was gentle and peaceable, full of meekneſs and charity. His great buſineſs was to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to others, to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt; <hi>he went about doing good,</hi> to the bodies, and to the ſouls of men: his miracles were not deſtructive to mankind, but healing and charitable. He could, if he had pleaſed, by his miraculous power have confounded his enemies, and have thundred out death and deſtruction againſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98129:8"/>the Infidel world, as his pretended <hi>Vicar</hi> hath ſince done againſt Hereticks. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that his Religion ſhould be propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated in human ways, and that Men ſhould be drawn to the profeſſion of it by the <hi>bands of love,</hi> and the <hi>cords of a man,</hi> by the gentle and peaceable methods of Reaſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion; he gave no example of a furious zeal and religious rage againſt thoſe who deſpiſed his Doctrine. It was propounded to men for their great advantage, and they rejected it at their utmoſt peril. It ſeemed good to the Author of this Inſtitution to compell no man to it by temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. When he went about making proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, he offered violence to no man, only ſaid, <hi>If any man will be my diſciple, If any man will come after me.</hi> And when his diſciples were leaving him, he does not ſet up an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition to torture and puniſh them for their defection from the faith; only ſays, <hi>Will ye alſo go away?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in imitation of this bleſſed Patern, the Chriſtian Church continued to ſpeak and act for ſeveral Ages. And this was the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98129:9"/>of the holy Fathers, <hi>Lex nova non
ſe vindicat ultore gladio,</hi> the Chriſtian Law doth not avenge it ſelf by the ſword. This was then the ſtyle of Councils, <hi>Nemini ad credendum vim inferre,</hi> to offer violence to no man to compel him to the faith. I proceed in the</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>
               <hi>Second</hi> place, to ſhew the <hi>Unjuſtifiable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this ſpirit upon any pretence whatſoever of zeal for God and Religion.</hi> No caſe can be put with Circumſtances of greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and more likely to juſtify this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and temper, than the caſe here in the Text. Thoſe againſt whom the diſciples would have <hi>called for fire from Heaven,</hi> were Hereticks and Schiſmaticks from the true Church; they had affronted our Saviour himſelf in his own perſon; the honour of God, and of that Religion which he had ſet up in the world, and of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which he had appointed for the place of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip were all concerned in this caſe: ſo that if ever it were warrantable to put on this fierce and furious zeal, here was a caſe that ſeemed to require it: But even in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98129:9"/>theſe circumſtances our Saviour thinks fit to rebuke and diſcountenance this ſpirit, <hi>Ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of.</hi> And he gives ſuch a Reaſon, as ought in all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Religion, how wide ſoever they be, to deter men from this temper, <hi>For the Son of man is not come to deſroy mens lives, but to ſave them;</hi> that is, this Spirit is utterly inconſiſtent with the great deſign of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, and the end of our Saviour's coming into the world.</p>
            <p>And now what hath the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to plead for her cruelty to men for the cauſe of Religion, which the Diſciples might not much better have pleaded for themſelves in their caſe? what hath ſhe to ſay againſt thoſe who are the objects of her cruelty and perſecution, which would not have held againſt the <hi>Samaritans?</hi> Does ſhe practice theſe ſeverities out of a zeal for truth, and for the honour of God, and Chriſt, and the true Religion? Why upon theſe very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts it was, that the Diſciples would have called for <hi>fire from Heaven</hi> to have deſtroyed the <hi>Samaritans.</hi> Is the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98129:10"/>that thoſe whom ſhe perſecutes are Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, and that no puniſhment can be too great for ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders? So the Diſciples were perſuaded of the <hi>Samaritans;</hi> and upon much better grounds: Only the Diſciples had ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe in their caſe, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath not; and that was Ignorance: And this apology our Saviour makes for them, <hi>ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of:</hi> They had been bred up in the Jewiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which gave ſome indulgence to this kind of temper, and they were able to cite a great Example for themſelves; beſides, they were then but learners, and not throughly inſtructed in the Chriſtian do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. But in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the caſe of particular perſons may be, as to the whole Church and the Governing part of it, this ignorance is wilful and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and therefore inexcuſable. For the Chriſtian Religion, which they profeſs to embrace, do's as plainly teach the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as it do's any other matter whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever: and it is not more evident in the New
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98129:10"/>Teſtament, that Chriſt died for ſinners, than that Chriſtians ſhould not kill one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other for the misbelief of any Article of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed</hi> Religion; much leſs, for the disbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of ſuch Articles as are <hi>invented</hi> by men, and impoſed as the Doctrines of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>You have heard what kind of <hi>Spirit</hi> it is, which our Saviour here reproves in his Diſciples. It was a furious and deſtructive <hi>Spirit,</hi> contrary to Chriſtian charity and goodneſs. But yet this may be ſaid in miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of their fault, that they themſelves offered no violence to their Enemies: They left it to God, and, no doubt, would have been very glad that he would have manifeſted his ſeverity upon them, by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down <hi>fire from Heaven</hi> to have conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them.</p>
            <p>But there is a much worſe <hi>Spirit</hi> than this in the world, which is not only contrary to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but to the common Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Natural Religion,</hi> and even to <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity</hi> it ſelf: Which by falſhood and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſfs, by ſecret plots and conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or by open ſedition and rebellion, by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98129:11"/>an Inquiſition or a Maſſacre; by depoſing and killing Kings, by fire and ſword, by the ruine of their Country, and betraying it into the hands of Foreigners; and, in a word, by diſſolving all the bonds of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society, and ſubverting the peace and order of the World, <hi>that is,</hi> by all the wicked wayes imaginable doth incite men to promote and advance their Religion. As if all the world were made for <hi>them,</hi> and there were not only no other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but no other Men beſides themſelves; as <hi>Babylon</hi> of old proudly vaunted, <hi>I am, and there is none beſides me:</hi> And as if the God, whom the Chriſtians worſhip, were not <hi>the God of order, but of Confuſion;</hi> as if he whom we call <hi>the Father of mercies</hi> were delighted with cruelty, and could not have a more pleaſing ſacrifice offered to him than a Maſſacre, nor put a greater honour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Prieſts then to make them Judges of an Inquiſition, <hi>that is,</hi> the inventers and decreers of torments for men more righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and innocent then themſelves.</p>
            <p>Thus to miſrepreſent God and Religion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98129:11"/>is to deveſt them of all their Majeſty and glory. For if that of <hi>Seneca</hi> be true, that <hi>ſine bonitate nulla majeſtas, without Goodneſs there can be no ſuch thing as Majeſty,</hi> then to ſeparate <hi>goodneſs</hi> and mercy from God, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> from Religion, is to make the <hi>two</hi> beſt things in the world, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> good for nothing.</p>
            <p>How much righter apprehenſions had the <hi>Heathen</hi> of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> which they looked upon as ſo benign and benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to mankind, that (as <hi>Tully</hi> admirably ſays) <hi>Dii immortales ad uſum hominum fabrefacti penè videantur, the nature of the immortal Gods may almoſt ſeem to be exactly framed for the benefit and advantage of men.</hi> And as for <hi>Religion,</hi> they always ſpeak of it as the great band of humane Society, and the foundation of truth, and fidelity, and juſtice among men. But when Religion once comes to ſupplant moral Righteouſneſs, and to teach men the abſurdeſt things in the world, <hi>to lye for the truth,</hi> and <hi>to kill men for God's ſake:</hi> when it ſerves to no other purpoſe, but to be a bond of conſpiracy, to inflame the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98129:12"/>of men to a greater fierceneſs, and to ſet a keener edge upon their ſpirits, and to make them <hi>ten times more the children of wrath</hi> and cruelty <hi>than they were by nature,</hi> then ſurely it loſes its nature and ceaſes to be <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:</hi> For let any man ſay worſe of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Infidelity,</hi> if he can. And, for God's ſake, what is Religion good for, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the manners and diſpoſitions of men, to reſtrain humane nature from violence and cruelty, from falſehood and treachery, from Sedition and Rebellion? Better it were there were no <hi>revealed</hi> Religion, and that humane nature were left to the conduct of its own principles and inclinations, which are much more mild &amp; merciful, much more for the peace and happineſs of humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; then to be acted by a Religion that inſpires men with ſo wild a fury, and prompts them to commit ſuch out-rages, and is continually ſupplanting Government, and undermining the welfare of mankind; in ſhort, ſuch a Religion as teaches men to propagate and advance it ſelf by <hi>means</hi> ſo evidently contrary to the very <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of all Religion.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98129:12"/>
            <p>And this, if it be well conſidered, will appear to be a very convincing way of reaſoning, by ſhewing the laſt reſult and conſequence of ſuch Principles, and of ſuch a Train of Propſitions, to be a moſt groſs and palpable abſurdity. <hi>For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> We will at preſent admit <hi>Popery</hi> to be the true Religion, and their <hi>Doctrines</hi> of <hi>extirpating Hereticks,</hi> of the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>depoſing Kings</hi> and ſubverting Government, by all the cruel and wicked ways that can be thought of, to be, as in truth they are, the Doctrines of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: In this Caſe, I would not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſelf to debate particulars; but if in the groſs, and upon the whole matter it be evident, that ſuch a Religion as this is as bad or worſe than Infidelity and no-Religion, this is conviction enough to a wiſe man, and as good as a Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that this is not the true Religion, and that it cannot be from God.</p>
            <p>How much better Teachers of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were the old <hi>Heathen Philoſophers?</hi> In all whoſe Books and Writings there is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98129:13"/>not one Principle to be found of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery or Rebellion; nothing that gives the leaſt countenance to an <hi>Aſſaſſination</hi> or a Maſſacre, to the betraying of ones Native Country, or the cutting of his Neighbours throat for difference in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. I ſpeak it with grief and ſhame, becauſe the credit of our common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is ſomewhat concerned in it, that <hi>Panaetius</hi> and <hi>Antipater</hi> and <hi>Diogenes</hi> the <hi>Stoick, Tully</hi> and <hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> were much honeſter and more Chriſtian <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> than the Jeſuits are, or the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> of any other <hi>Order,</hi> that I know of, in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I come now in the</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/>
               <hi>Third</hi> and laſt place, to make ſome <hi>Application</hi> of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let not Religion ſuffer for thoſe faults and miſcarriages which really pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the ignorance of Religion, and from the want of it. That under colour and pretence of Religion, very bad things
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98129:13"/>are done, is no argument that Religion it ſelf is not good: Becauſe the beſt things are liable to be perverted and abuſed to very ill purpoſes, nay <hi>the corruption of them is commonly the worſt;</hi> as, they ſay, the richeſt and nobleſt Wines make the ſharpeſt Vinegar. <hi>If the light that is in you,</hi> ſays our Saviour, <hi>be darkneſs, how great is that darkneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us beware of that <hi>Church</hi> which countenanceth this <hi>unchriſtian ſpirit</hi> here condemned by our Saviour; and which teaches ſuch <hi>Doctrines,</hi> and warrants ſuch <hi>Practices</hi> as are conſonant thereto. You all know, without my ſaying ſo, that I mean the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> in which are taught ſuch <hi>Doctrines</hi> as theſe, That Hereticks, <hi>that is</hi> all who differ from them in matters of Faith, are to be extirpated by fire and ſword; which was decreed in the <hi>third</hi> and <hi>fourth Lateran</hi> Councils, where all Chriſtians are ſtrictly charged to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour this to the uttermoſt of their power, <hi>Sicut reputari cupiunt &amp; haberi fideles, as they deſire to be eſteemed and accounted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98129:14"/>Chriſtians.</hi> Next their <hi>Doctrines</hi> of depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Kings,</hi> and of <hi>abſolving their ſubjects from obedience to them;</hi> which were not only univerſally believed, but practiſed by the <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Church for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ages<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Indeed this Doctrine hath not been at all times alike frankly and openly avowed, but it is undoubtedly theirs; and hath frequently been put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though they have not thought it ſo convenient at all turns to make profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it. It is a certain kind of Engine, which is to be ſcru'd up or let down, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſerves; and is commonly kept like <hi>Goliah's</hi> Sword in the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> but yet ſo that the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> can lend it out upon an extraordinary occaſion.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Practices<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> conſonant to theſe <hi>Doctrines,</hi> I ſhall go no further than the horrid and bloody <hi>Deſign</hi> of this <hi>Day.</hi> Such a <hi>Myſtery</hi> of Iniquity, as had been <hi>hid from ages and generations;</hi> Such a Maſter-piece of Villany, <hi>as eye had not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor ever</hi> before <hi>entred into the heart of man:</hi> So prodigiouſly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98129:14"/>Barbarous, both in the ſubſtance and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of it, as is not to be parallell'd in all the voluminous Records of Time, from the foundation of the World.</p>
            <p>Of late years our <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> for ſo they have made themſelves without any provocation of ours, have almoſt had the impudence to deny ſo plain a matter of fact; but I wiſh they have not taken an effectual courſe, by freſh Conſpiracies, of equal or greater horrour, to confirm the belief of it with a witneſs. But I ſhall not anticipate what will be more proper for another <hi>Day,</hi> but confine my ſelf to the preſent Occaſion.</p>
            <p>I will not trouble you with the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Narrative of this dark Conſpiracy, nor the obſcure manner of its diſcovery, which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf acknowledges not to have been <hi>without a Miracle.</hi> Let us thank God that it was ſo happily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and diſappointed, as I hope their preſent deſign will be, by the ſame won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and merciful providence of God towards a moſt unworthy People. And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98129:15"/>may the <hi>lameneſs</hi> and halting of
<hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> the Founder of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver depart from that <hi>Order,</hi> but be a <hi>Fate</hi> continually attending all their villanous Plots and Contrivances.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only obſerve to you, that after the diſcovery of this Plot the Authors of it were not convinced of the evil, but ſorry for the miſcarriage of it. Sir <hi>Everard Digby,</hi> whoſe very original Papers and Letters are now in my hands, after he was in Priſon, and knew he muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, calls it <hi>the beſt Cauſe;</hi> and was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely troubled to hear it <hi>cenſured by Catholicks and Prieſts, contrary to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, for a great ſin: Let me tell you,</hi> ſays he, <hi>what a grief it is, to hear THAT ſo much condemned, which I did believe would have been otherwiſe thought of by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks.</hi> And yet he concludes that <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> with theſe words, <hi>In how full joy ſhould I dye, if I could do any thing for the Cauſe which I love more than my life.</hi> And, in another <hi>Letter,</hi> he ſays, he could have ſaid ſomething to have mitigated
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98129:15"/>the <hi>odium</hi> of this buſineſs, as to that Point of involving thoſe of his own Religion in the common ruine, <hi>I dare not</hi> (ſays he) <hi>take that courſe that I could to make it appear leſs odious, for divers were to have been brought out of danger, who now would rather hurt them than otherwiſe. I do not think there would have been three worth the ſaving that ſhould have been loſt.</hi> And as to the reſt, that were to have been ſwallow'd up in that deſtruction, he ſeems not to have the leaſt relenting in his mind about them. All doubts he ſeems to have look'd upon as temptations, and <hi>intreats</hi> his Friends <hi>to pray for the pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his not ſufficient ſtriving againſt temptations ſince this buſieneſs was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good God! that any thing that is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion ſhould ſo perfectly ſtrip men of all humanity, and transform the mild and gentle race of mankind into ſuch Wolves and Tigers: that ever a pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed zeal for Thy glory ſhould inſtigate men to diſhonour Thee at ſuch a rate.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98129:16"/>It is believed by many, and not without cauſe, that the Pope and his Faction are the <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> I will ſay no more than I know in this matter; I am not ſure that it is <hi>he</hi> that is particularly deſigned in Scripture by that Name; but however that be, I challenge <hi>Antichriſt</hi> himfelf, whoever he be, and whenever he comes, to do worſe and wickeder things than theſe.</p>
            <p>But I muſt remember my <hi>Text,</hi> and take heed of imitating that <hi>Spirit</hi> which is there condemned, whilſt I am inveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt it. And in truth it almoſt looks uncharitably to ſpeak the truth in theſe matters, and barely to relate what theſe men have not bluſh'd to do. I need not, nay I cannot, aggravate theſe things, they are too horrible in themſelves, even when they are expreſs'd in the ſofreſt and gentleſt words.</p>
            <p>I would not be underſtood to charge every particular perſon who is, or hath been, in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, with the guilt of theſe or the like practiſes: But I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98129:16"/>muſt charge their Doctrines and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with them; I muſt charge the <hi>Heads</hi> of their Church, and the prevalent <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>governing</hi> part of it, who are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the contrivers and abetters, the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners and applauders of theſe curſed Deſigns.</p>
            <p>I do willingly acknowledg the great Piety and Charity of ſeveral perſons who have lived and dyed in that Communion, as <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> Father, <hi>Paul, Thuanus,</hi> and many others; who had in truth more goodneſs than the Principles of that Religion do either incline men to, or allow of. And yet he that conſiders how univerſally al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> were engaged in that <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> which is ſtill freſh in our memories, will find it very hard to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine how many degrees of innocency and good nature, or of coldneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency in Religion, are neceſſary to overballance the fury of a blind zeal and a miſguided Conſcience.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but <hi>Papiſts</hi> are made like other men. Nature hath not generally gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98129:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>them ſuch ſavage and cruel diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but their Religion hath made them ſo. Whereas true Chriſtianity is not only the beſt, but the beſt-natur'd Inſtitution in the world; and ſo far as any Church is departed from good nature, and become cruel and barbarous, ſo far is it degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Chriſtianity. I am loth to ſay it, and yet I am conſident 'tis very true, That many <hi>Papiſts</hi> would have been excellent perſons, and very good men, if their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion had not hindered them; if the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Principles of their Church had not perverted and ſpoiled their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſpoſitions.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not this to exaſperate <hi>You, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Patriots, and the great Bulwark of our Religion,</hi> to any <hi>unreaſonable</hi> or <hi>unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary,</hi> much leſs <hi>unchriſtian</hi> Severities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: No, let us not do like them; let us never do any thing for Religion that is contrary to it: But I ſpeak it to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken your care thus far, That if their <hi>Prieſts</hi> will always be putting theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Principles into the minds of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98129:17"/>
               <hi>People,</hi> effectual Proviſion may be made, that it may never be in their power again to put them in practiſe. We have found by experience, that ever ſince the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> they have been continually peck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the foundations of our Peace and Religion: When God knows we have been ſo far from thirſting after their blood, that we did not ſo much as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire their diſquiet, but in order to our own neceſſary ſafety, and indeed to theirs.</p>
            <p>And God be praiſed for thoſe match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Inſtances which we are able to give of the generous humanity and Chriſtian temper of the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants.</hi> After Q. <hi>Maryes</hi> death, when the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was reſtored, Biſhop <hi>Bonner,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his Cruelties and But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, was permitted quietly to live and dye amongſt us. And after the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of this <hi>Day,</hi> nay at this very time, ſince the diſcovery of ſo barbarous a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and the higheſt provocation in the world, by the treacherous murder of one
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98129:18"/>of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Juſtices of the Peace, a very good Man, and a moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, who had been active in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this Plot; I ſay, after all this, and notwithſtanding the continued and inſupportable inſolence of their carriage and behaviour, even upon this occaſion, no violence, nay not ſo much as any inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, that I ever heard of, hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to any of them. I would to God they would but ſeriouſly conſider this one dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between <hi>our</hi> Religion and <hi>theirs,</hi> and which of them comes neareſt to <hi>the Wiſdom which is from above,</hi> which is <hi>peaceable,</hi> and gentle, and <hi>full of mercy.</hi> And I do heartily pray, and have good hopes, that upon this occaſion God will open their eyes ſo far, as to convince a great many among them, that <hi>that</hi> cannot be the true Religion which inſpires men with ſuch barbarous minds.</p>
            <p>I have now done, and if I have been tranſported upon this Argument ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what beyond my uſual temper, the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this <hi>Day,</hi> and our preſent cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98129:18"/>will, I hope, bear me out. I have expreſſed my ſelf all along with a juſt ſenſe, and with no unjuſt ſeverity, concerning theſe horrid Principles and Practiſes; but yet with great pity and tenderneſs towards thoſe miſerably ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Souls, who have been deluded by them, and enſnared in them. And I can truly ſay, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Orator did of himſelf upon another occaſion, <hi>Me natura miſericordem, patria ſeverum, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delem nec patria nec natura eſſe voluit.</hi> My nature enclines me to be tender and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate; a hearty zeal for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and concernment for the publique welfare of my Countrey, may perhaps have made me a little ſevere; but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my natural diſpoſition, nor the temper of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, nor the <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant, that is</hi> the true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, will allow me to be cruel.</p>
            <p>For the future, Let us <hi>encourage our ſelves in the Lord our God;</hi> and <hi>commit</hi> our Cauſe, and <hi>the keeping of our Souls
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98129:19"/>to Him in well doing:</hi> And, under God, let us leave it to the wiſdom and care of His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and His two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to make a laſting Proviſion for the ſecurity of our Peace and Religion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the ſecret contrivances and open attempts of <hi>theſe ſons of violence.</hi> And let us remember thoſe words of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 37.12, 13, 14, 15, <hi>The wicked plotteth againſt the juſt, and gnaſheth upon him with his teeth: The Lord ſhall laugh at him, for he ſeeth that his day is coming. The wicked have drawn out the ſword, and bent their bow, to caſt down the poor and needy, and to ſlay ſuch as be of upright converſation: Their ſword ſhall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own heart, and their bowes ſhall be broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I hope, conſidering what God hath heretofore done, and hath now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to do for us, we may take encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our ſelves, againſt all the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Religion, which are confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated againſt us, in the words of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.9, 10, <hi>Aſſociate your ſelves,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98129:19"/>O ye People, and ye ſhall be broken in pieces, and give ear, all ye of far Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys: Gird your ſelves, and ye ſhall be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in pieces: Gird your ſelves, and ye ſhall be broken in pieces: Take counſel together, and it ſhall come to naught: Speak the word and it ſhall not ſtand: FOR GOD IS WITH <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now what remains? But to make our moſt devout and thankful acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable bleſſing of our <hi>Reformed</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and for the miraculous <hi>Deliverance</hi> of this <hi>Day,</hi> and for the wonderful <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery</hi> of the late horrid and barbarous <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> againſt our <hi>Prince,</hi> our <hi>Peace,</hi> and our <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Him <hi>therefore, our moſt gracious and merciful God, our</hi> Shield, and <hi>our</hi> Rock, <hi>and our mighty</hi> Deliverer: <hi>Who hath</hi> brought us out of the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and out of the Houſe of bondage; <hi>and hath ſet us free from</hi> Popiſh <hi>Tyranny and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition,</hi> a yoke which neither we nor our Fathers were able to bear.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98129:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Who hath, from time to time, delivered us from the bloody and mercileſs deſigns</hi> of wicked and unreaſonable men; <hi>and hath render'd all the plots and contrivances, the miſchievous</hi> counſels and devices, <hi>of theſe</hi> worſe-than-Heathens, <hi>of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who, did, as upon this</hi> Day, <hi>reſcue our</hi> King <hi>and our</hi> Princes, <hi>our</hi> Nobles <hi>and the</hi> Heads of our Tribes, <hi>the</hi> Governours <hi>of our</hi> Church <hi>and the</hi> Judges <hi>of the</hi> Land, <hi>from that fearful Deſtruction which was ready to have ſwallowed them up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſtill</hi> brings to light the hidden things of darkneſs, <hi>and hath hitherto pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved our</hi> Religion <hi>and</hi> Civil <hi>intereſts to us, in deſpite of all the malicious and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs attempts of our Adverſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto that great</hi> God, <hi>who hath done ſo great things for us, and hath ſaved us by a mighty</hi> Salvation: <hi>Who</hi> hath delivered us, and doth deliver us, and, we truſt, will ſtill deliver us; <hi>he glory and honour, thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving and praiſe, from generation to genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And let all the People ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98129:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
